Malcolm X and Ho Chi Minh, two great revolutionaries who fought against colonialism and oppression,
were both born on 19 May. However, a closer look at their political history and ideas
reveal that they shared more than just a birthday. Malcolm X, born Malcolm Little on 19 May 1925,
in Omaha, Nebraska, was born into a political family. His parents, Earl and Luis Little,
were active members of the United Negro Improvement Association, or the UNIA,
an organization founded by the Honorable Marcus Mosiah Garvey. Marcus Garvey was one of the 20th
century's most prominent Pan-African leaders, and at its height, the UNIA had up to 6 million
members worldwide. Its members were Africans, whether on the continent or in the diaspora,
who believed that Africa belongs to African people, and that Africa must unite into one
Pan-African state known as the United States of Africa, so that all Africans in the diaspora,
dedicated to the cause, may one day return home and join their sisters and brothers on the continent.
Marcus Garvey had a tremendous impact on the Pan-African movement historically and into the present.
However, Africans were not the only ones inspired by Marcus Garvey's ideas. Ho Chi Minh, born on 19 May,
1890, in what was then the French colony of Indochina, also became a huge admirer of Marcus Garvey.
Marcus Garvey even played a role in his decision to fight for the liberation of his people in Vietnam.
In the 1920s, Ho Chi Minh was a student of Columbia University in New York City. As a working-class
person from a colonized background, he lived in and spent his time in Harlem, a massive hub of UNIA
activities. He reportedly attended many lectures given by Marcus Garvey during this time, shaping his early
political thought. He even wrote several essays that are now compiled in a collection called The
Black Race. The 20 essays in the book explain the history of oppression against black people,
from slavery to Jim Crow. Ultimately, Malcolm X and Ho Chi Minh were closely united in their
conviction that colonized and oppressed people must fight for national liberation. Malcolm X became one of
the first Pan-African voices to denounce U.S. intervention in Vietnam. He declared that the United States,
complete defeat in South Vietnam is only a matter of time, and said, I think young people here can
find the powerful example in the young Simbas in the Congo and the young fighters in South Vietnam.